Register of the Nezavisimost' records
Hoover Institution Archives
Nezavisimost' records
1988-2001
2008C89
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes (1.7 linear feet)
Internal circulated material, protocols, correspondence, flyers, serial issues, and printed matter relating to the labor movement in the Soviet Union and post-Soviet Russia.
Nezavisimost'.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2008.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
Nezavisimost' was one of the first independent trade unions in the Soviet Union that emphasized workers' control over wages and factory administration.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Nezavisimost' records consist of internal circulated material, protocols, correspondence, flyers, serial issues, and other printed matter relating to the labor movement in the Soviet Union and post-Soviet Russia. The collection also includes information on workers' protests in the early 1990s, including the Poliustrovo strike in 1991.
The original folder titles given by the creator have been maintained. Within individual folders, materials have been kept in their original order as accumulated by the creator. File 33 ("Kak sozdat' profsoiuz "Nezavisimost'" na predpriiatii") and File 38 ("Kharman, K., "Rossiia: kak revoliutsiia byla proigrana") were not received.
Labor movement--Russia (Federation); Labor movement--Soviet Union.
- File 1: "Spravka po arkhivu Nezavisimosti s prilozheniiami k nei,", 1989-1992 (Box-folder 1: 1-2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes biographical note and photographs of political activists from Saint Petersburg who were involved in establishing the independent trade union Nezavisimost'.
- File 2: "Uchreditel'nye dokumenty Poliustrovskoi Nezavisimosti,", 1989-1990 (Box-folder 1: 3)
- File 3: "Iskhodiashchie dokumenty Poliustrovskoi Nezavisimosti,", 1991-1993 (Box-folder 1: 4)
- File 4: "Vkhodiashchie dokumenty Poliustrovskoi Nezavisimosti,", 1991-1993 (Box-folder 1: 5)
- File 5: "Materialy po zabastovke na PPSK (Proektno-promyshlennoe stroitel'noe ob"edinenie DSK-2),", 1991 (Box-folder 1: 6-7)
- File 6: "Podriadnaia deiatel'nost' Poliustrovskoi Nezavisimosti,", 1992-1993 (Box-folder 1: 8)
- File 7: "Protokoly sobranii Poliustrovskoi Nezavisimosti,", 1990-1994 (Box-folder 1: 9-11, Box-folder 4: 11-12)
- File 8: "Listovki i drugie materialy Nezavisimosti,", 1990-1992 (Box-folder 2: 1)
- File 9: "Individual'nye dogovory,", 1992-1993 (Box-folder 2: 2)
- File 10: "Inaia dokumentatsiia,", 1989-1992 (Box-folder 2: 3)
- File 11: "Normativnye akty i zakony,", 1991-1992 (Box-folder 2: 4-6)
- File 12: "Vybory v Gosudarstvennuiu Dumu,", 1993 (Box-folder 2: 7)
- File 13: "Materialy dlia gazety,", 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2: 8-9)
  Includes manuscripts and typescripts of articles.
- File 14: "OOO (Obshchestvo s Ogranichennoi Otvetstvennost'iu) Trio,", 1992-1993 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  Includes financial documents.
- File 15: "Galeev, Igor' Aleksandrovich,", 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2: 11)
- File 16: "Gubaidullin, Akhtiam Gadievich,", 1991-1993 (Box-folder 2: 12)
- File 17: "Ikhlov, Boris,", 1990-1994 (Box-folder 2: 13)
- File 18: "KAS-KOR i Konfederatsiia SSSR,", 1990-1993 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  Includes correspondence from KAS-KOR (Informational Bulletin of the Workers’ and Syndicalists’ Movement).
- File 19: "Leskov, Arii Feofilovich,", 1992-1993 (Box-folder 3: 1)
- File 20: "Moskalev, Aleksandr Maksimovich,", 1990-1993 (Box-folder 3: 2)
- File 21: "Nikonov, Aleksandr Petrovich,", 1991-1993 (Box-folder 3: 3)
- File 22: "Sotsialisty iz SShA i Anglii,", 1989-1993 (Box-folder 3: 4-5)
  Includes correspondence and printed matter.
- File 23: "Fominykh, Ekaterina Nikolaevna,", 1990-1991 (Box-folder 3: 6)
- File 24: "Fonchenko, A. V.,", 1993 (Box-folder 3: 7)
- File 25: "Cherviakov, Aleksandr A.,", 1990-1991 (Box-folder 3: 8)
- File 26: "Cherkasov, Vladimir Semenovich,", 1990-1991 (Box-folder 3: 9)
- File 27: "Korpunkt,", 1990-1991 (Box-folder 3: 10-11)
- File 28: "Vorkuta,", 1989-1990 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  Includes photographs, correspondence, and clippings relating to the Nezavisimost' activities at Vorgoshorskaia mining company in Vorkuta.
- File 29: "Samara,", 1990-1991 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  Includes information on workers' protests at the Zavod imeni Maslennikova in Samara.
- File 30: "Raznoe,", 1988-1992 (Box-folder 3: 14-15)
  Includes correspondence and writings submitted to the Nezavisimost'.
- File 31: "Pensionnoe obespechenie iz obosoblennogo sotsstrakha Nezavisimosti (Metodicheskaia razrabotka),", 1992 (Box-folder 3: 16)
- File 32: "Barskii, E. S., "alant i klass," typescript, circa 1990 (Box-folder 3: 17)
- File 33: Not received
- File 34: "Svoboda v ramkakh otvetstvennosti: ptogramma printsipov,", 1994 (Box-folder 4: 1)
- File 35: "Programma sotsial'nykh garantii profsoiuza Nezavisimost', ch. 1: Postroenie obosoblennogo sotsstrakha,", 1991 (Box-folder 4: 2)
- File 36: "Ustav professional'noi assotsiatsii rabochikh Nezavisimost',", 1989 (Box-folder 4: 3)
- File 37: "Ustav mezhdunarodnoi professional'noi assotsiatsii rabochikh Nezavisimost', Rossiiskaia Nezavisimost',", 1989 (Box-folder 4: 4)
- File 38: Not received
- File 39: "Zabastovki,", 1997-1998 (Box-folder 4: 5-7)
- File 40: "Sudebnye dela "Egidy',", 1999-2001 (Box-folder 4: 8-10)